Why are there zombies here?
為什麼會有殭屍？
I can't take this.
我受不了了
Are you already…
你該不會…
I'm still okay.
我沒事
Incoming!
看我的
Wait for me, Mom and Dad!
爸、媽，等等我
I'll be there soon!
我馬上就過去
Charo!
茶六！
Where are you, Charo?
茶六，你在哪裡？
Charo.
茶六
Charo!
茶六！
Now is not the time to be humping things!
現在不是騎東西的時候
I was so worried about you!
人家好擔心你
It's dangerous to run off on your own!
妳自己一個人跑掉太危險了
But…
但是…
Mommy and Daddy are already…
爸爸媽媽都已經…
Charo is all I have left!
我只剩下茶六而已了
Anyway, it isn't safe here.
總之，這裡不安全
All right!
好了！
I doubt those zombies can climb ladders!
我想那些殭屍總不會爬梯子吧
Now we just wait until the electric fence is deactivated.
只好在這裡等到電籬笆斷電了
Mr. Kencho, over there.
憲一哥哥，那裡
You're…
你是…
You're going down.
你摔下去吧
Each day, there was nothing for me.
我沒有歸屬，每天無處棲身
I fell farther and farther until I reached the pit of misfortune.
跌得越來越深，一路跌到谷底
That's why you're going to go down with me!
所以你們就跟我一起去死吧！
Mr. Kencho!
憲一哥哥！
Just fall from here and become zombie food!
掉下去成為殭屍的食物吧
I need to do whatever it takes to stop the water wheel!
我必須設法快讓水車停下來才能斷電
I see it!
看到了！
Curios from the Warring States Period are nothing more than junk,
戰國時期的古董在我眼中
especially against me.
不過就是垃圾
I was in the top four in the high school Kendo Nationals two years in a row.
我可是連續兩年 在全國高中劍道賽進入四強呢
Your samurai fangirling is no match against me.
妳這個武士道迷妹根本不是我的對手
Mrs. Tome! Old Man Hiko!
留！彥老爹！
We have to hurry and evacuate the village!
我們得快點撤離村子
Shizuka!
閑
If a horde of zombies come, they'll break through this thin wooden door!
如果殭屍大軍來到這裡 這道薄薄的木門是擋不住他們的
Shizuka, calm down and listen.
閑，冷靜下來聽我說
We're all old and we have difficulty moving around.
我們全都年紀大了，行動不便
Old Man Hiko is mostly bedridden so we can't carry him.
彥老爹幾乎都臥病在床 我們也帶不了他
Listen, Shizuka.
聽著，閑
Don't worry about us old-timers who don't have much time left.
別擔心我們這些時日不多的老人了
Please. You must try to survive.
拜託妳一定要努力活下去
No way.
這樣怎麼行
At this rate, Mrs. Tome and the others will be…
依照這個速度，大家很快就會…
Geez!
可惡！
Over here, you dumb zombies!
你們這些蠢殭屍給我過來
-Shizuka? -I'll get you out of there.
-閑？ -我一定會救你們出去的
So don't give up!
所以千萬不要放棄
I didn't analyze the risks at all!
我完全沒有先評估風險啊！
It's definitely because of those happy-go-lucky dorks!
一定是那些樂天的傻蛋害的
The door won't hold for much longer!
這道門撐不了多久了
Incoming!
看我的！
Akira!
輝！
I haven't done enough yet!
我做的還不夠
I didn't make enough to send you much money.
我賺的不夠多，沒辦法寄錢回家
I never took you on any trips overseas.
我從不曾帶你們出國旅遊
I haven't found anyone to marry yet.
就算想結婚也還沒找到對象
So giving you grandkids is a long way off.
所以要給你們抱孫子還早得很
I haven't done enough for you yet!
我為你們做的還不夠
I'm not going to apologize in front of your graves.
我不會等到在你們的墳前才後悔的
There are so many things
我還有很多事
I want to do while you're still alive!
要趁你們活著的時候做
You greenhorn.
乳臭未乾的小子
Dad?
爸爸？
You want to repay us that badly?
你就這麼想回報我們？
Then don't die before your parents.
那就不許比父母先死
Take care of your mom.
好好照顧你媽
Da…
爸…
Dad!
爸爸！
Hey, come on, it's okay.
來嘛，沒關係啦
I don't want to go home yet.
我還不想回家
-I guess I have no choice. -Not wanting to go home…
-看來沒得選了 -不想回家…
I feel the same way.
我也有同樣的感覺
WEDDING PHOTOS
（婚禮寫真）
Like anybody, when I first got married, I wanted a happy home.
我跟所有人一樣 新婚時都想有個安穩幸福的家
But before I realized it, that place stopped being my home.
但是不知不覺間 那個地方已經再也容不下我
So, everyday I killed some time at bars and internet cafés before going home.
所以我每天都會流連酒吧 和網咖殺時間，然後才回家
My car was the only place where I could relax.
如今，車子裡是我唯一能放鬆的地方
I heard that Mrs. Yoneda's husband was promoted to section chief.
聽說米田太太的老公升上課長了
Her whole family is going to Singapore over the long weekend. Isn't that nice?
他們這個連假全家要去新加坡玩 是不是很棒？
Anyway, we're going out to eat as a family.
總之，我們全家要一起出去吃飯了
My relationship with my wife had already gone cold.
我和妻子的感情早已降到冰點
We would talk about once a week, but it'd only be snide remarks or name-calling.
我們一週最多只會講上一次話 但不是在嘲諷就是吵架
I no longer had the energy to repair my relationships.
我已經沒有動力再去修復關係
I wondered why I was working myself to the bone
我不知道自己為了不愛也不關心的家
for a family I had lost all love and affection for?
這樣天天拼死拼活地工作 到底是為了什麼？
My wife is such a bitch!
混帳老婆
Whenever she talks,
她每次開口
it's to nag me to keep the bathroom clean or to hurry to get a promotion.
只會唸我別弄髒廁所或要我趕快升官
Shut up already!
囉嗦死了！
I found you!
找到妳了！
A girl and I alone in a place like this.
落單女孩和我一起待在這樣的地方
I'm so lucky.
我真是幸運
Lucky? What do you mean by that?
幸運？這是什麼意思？
The thing I want to do most is to "force my tongue down a girl's throat."
我最想做的事 就是“強迫女孩子跟我舌吻”
7. FORCE MY TONGUE DOWN A GIRL'S THROAT
（七：強迫女孩子跟我舌吻）
This is even worse than a zombie!
這比殭屍還噁心
You're not getting away!
妳跑不掉的！
What's the problem? It's just a French kiss!
怎麼了？不過是法式舌吻嘛
It's no big deal!
沒什麼大不了的
No way! Absolutely not!
不可以，絕對不可以
I'd rather be eaten by zombies than be French kissed by that guy!
我寧願被殭屍吃掉 也不想跟那傢伙法式舌吻
I've never had luck with women or money.
女人和金錢方面我從來沒走運過
I've had nothing but bad luck all my life.
這輩子除了衰只有衰
I'm saying goodbye to that unlucky life!
這下要跟不幸的人生說再見了
-Five covers! -Is the pasta ready yet?
-五份生火腿 -義大利麵好了嗎？
-Carpaccio at table number seven. -Come on! The orders are piling up!
-生牛肉薄片Sette -拜託，點單越積越多了
Excuse me.
不好意思
Was "sette" supposed to be six?
剛剛是說六份嗎？
Listen, you haven't learned a single number yet.
聽著，你到現在都還學不會數字
How are you going to take orders?
這樣要怎麼接單？
But no one taught me anything.
但是大家什麼都沒教我
And besides they could just tell me in Japanese, right?
況且，用日語說不就得了？
-He's making excuses again. -He's always doing this.
-又在找藉口 -每次都這樣
Why are the senior workers and the owner so mean to me?
為什麼老闆 和那些前輩都對我這麼壞？
I've got the worst luck.
我運氣真是夠背的
Oops.
唉呀
They're going to bitch about how that's not the way good chefs behave.
他們一定又會囉嗦說好廚師該怎樣的
This is why I told them we should put ashtrays in the kitchen.
所以我才說廚房裡應該要放菸灰缸嘛
Looks like I'm getting fired again.
看來我又要被開除了
I've really got the worst luck.
運氣真是夠背的
So what if the restaurant burned down because I forgot to put out my cigarette?
我只是沒熄菸 害餐廳燒光光，那又怎樣啦？
I lost my job just like everyone else!
我還不是跟其他人一樣失去了工作
I don't see why they had to get so mad at me!
我真搞不懂他們 為什麼一定要對我那麼生氣
No matter how you think about it, I'm the unlucky one!
不論怎麼想，我才是最倒楣的人吧？
Old Man Hiko?
彥老爹？
Akemi?
明美？
Not bad.
還不差嘛
I can barely parry.
我只能勉強擋下攻擊
The problem with this baby is that it attracts zombies with the noise it makes.
這個寶貝的缺點 就是聲音會引來殭屍
So let's make this quick.
所以我們速戰速決吧
Why would you do something so evil?
妳為什麼要做出這麼邪惡的事？
Evil?
邪惡？
I'm only doing what's right!
我只是在做對的事
But everyone just complains about me!
但是大家都只會抱怨我
Mr. Takaoka, the glue stick goes next to the stapler.
高岡先生，口紅膠要放在釘書機旁邊
I've warned you countless times, haven't I?
我已經提醒過你很多次了吧？
Section chief, I can't believe you're rejecting my plan.
課長，你竟然駁回我提出的企劃案
This workplace is barely functioning!
這個辦公室的水準未免也太差了吧
Department chief,
部長
should you be letting people who make such mistakes slide?
你怎麼可以讓這種 有問題的人事異動強行通過？
Was it the usual?
一如往常嗎？
She did it again. Wow.
她又來了
It's really exhausting working with her, isn't it?
和她一起工作真累人呢，你說對吧？
She's so self-righteous and pushy about it!
她自以為正義，又愛堅持己見
Shut up.
閉嘴
You coddled snowflakes are the ones at fault!
錯的是你們這些從小被寵壞的傢伙！
What have we ever done to you?
你說說看我們對你做了什麼啊？
-Quit blaming others for your problems-- -I'm the victim here!
-少胡亂遷怒無關的人… -我才是受害者
"I am the victim in the marriage"? Don't make me laugh!
說什麼“我是婚姻的受害者”？
Just because she couldn't reach me when she gave birth?
就因為她生產時連絡不到我？ 那又怎樣？
I was entertaining clients when I didn't want to!
我又不是自己想要招待客戶的！
She continued to hold a grudge about how scared she was being by herself!
她一天到晚只會埋怨 當初自己一個人有多害怕
No matter how you think about it, I'm the victim!
不論怎麼想，我才是受害者啊
I thought that was the case!
果然如我所料
You can badmouth your woman however you like,
想怎麼抱怨你家女人都隨便你
but have you given her even a single flower for a wedding anniversary?
但是你結婚紀念日有送過花嗎？
Have you thanked her for taking care of the house every day
你有謝過她每天處理家務嗎？
or listened to her complaints or true feelings?
你有傾聽她的抱怨跟心裡話嗎？
Did you ever treat her like she was the queen of your universe?
我在問你有沒有把她 當作你的女王好好對待？
The reason she lost interest in you is because you let her down!
她會對你失去興趣 都是因為你讓她失望
You never made an effort to love her.
你從來沒有為了愛她而付出
You never gave her anything, and you expected her to take care of you?
什麼都沒給她 卻還期望她會照顧你？
She's not your mother!
她又不是你的媽咪！
Shut up!
給我閉嘴！
Enough of that!
說夠了
You two are going down with me!
你們兩個要跟我一起墜入深淵
Fine.
好吧
If you want to go down, I'll go down with you as you wish!
你這麼想下去 我就順你的意陪你一起下去
Mr. Kencho!
憲一哥哥！
What the hell are you thinking?
你到底在想什麼？
What's triggering the zombies to attack us?
是什麼觸發殭屍攻擊我們？
Our movements? Our smell? Or is it our body heat?
我們的動作？味道？還是體溫？
It doesn't matter what it is.
都無所謂了！
If I want to mask all of that, this is my only option!
如果想隱藏那些東西 這就是唯一的選項
Wha…
什…
You're joking, right? Head first?
你在開玩笑吧？竟然從頭先下去？
No. Stop!
不要，快停下！
Stay away!
不要過來！
If you're going to go down, don't choose a pit of despair.
既然都要往下跳 別選擇跳進不幸的深淵
If you had chosen the cesspit, you could've avoided becoming a zombie.
選擇跳進糞坑 你就能避免成為殭屍了
Don't come near me until you've taken a bath.
你洗澡前別靠近我
Akemi?
明美？
Where did Akemi go?
明美去哪裡了？
Old Man Hiko,
彥老爹
Shizuka is using herself as bait to protect us from the zombies.
閑把自己當作誘餌 保護我們不被殭屍攻擊
And? What are you all still doing here?
然後呢？你們還在這裡做什麼？
What are we doing?
什麼意思？
We're old. We can't move as well as we'd like to.
我們這群上了年紀 無法行動自如的老人
Even if we went to save her…
就算出去救她…
Has anything ever gone the way we wanted it to?
哪有什麼事情曾如我們的願？
Large-scale projects declined following the post-war land reform,
戰後土地改革使得大規模農作式微
and the TPP was looming.
又擔心跨太平洋夥伴協定的問題
We were unsure of who our successors would be.
也不知道誰能繼承家業
Even so, we desperately clung to our hoes and managed, didn't we?
儘管如此，我們還是緊緊抓著鋤頭 繼續過日子，不是嗎？
Typhoons, sweltering heat, freezing cold…
颱風、高溫、寒害
No matter how many times nature ferociously tried to beat us down,
不論大自然想狠狠擊倒我們幾次
we'd grit our teeth and say, "This is the year!"
我們仍咬緊牙根說：“今年一定行”
We've survived this long, haven't we?
我們都撐這麼久了，不是嗎？
Who cares about some zombies?
誰在乎那幾個殭屍？
Hey, are you aware of the recognitive hyper-focalization theory?
你聽過“認知焦點化理論”嗎？
Recogni… What?
認知…那是什麼？
It's a theory that attempts to scientifically define luck.
這個理論嘗試 用科學的角度來解釋運氣
Do you only care about yourself?
你是不是都只會想到自己？
Does your concern extend to family, lovers, friends or complete strangers?
你的關心有沒有延伸到家人 愛人、朋友，甚至是陌生人？
All that matters is today? Or Tomorrow too?
你是不是只有想到今天？那明天呢？
Are you considering the next generation or society as a whole?
你會不會為下一代或整體社會著想？
When you face a challenge, who else do you consider?
面臨挑戰時 你會不會顧慮到身邊的人？
The larger the scope of your consideration, the more luck you have.
考慮的範圍越廣，你的運氣就會越好
Showing off how smart you are even at a time like this?
都到了這種時候還在愛現？
Who cares about any of that?
誰在乎那些事啊？
At this very moment, I'm the lucky one!
此時此刻，走運的是我
You're the one with bad luck!
倒楣的人是妳
CAUTION FIRE DANGER
（當心起火危險）
Old Man Hiko!
彥老爹！
You really are the finest hunter in the village!
你真不愧是村子裡最厲害的獵人
That was just a lucky shot! What's one old man going to do?
那槍只是走運而已 一個老頭能做什麼？
Who the hell are you guys?
你們是哪位啊？
Anyone who gets rough with our Shizuka…
誰敢傷害我們的閑
…gets no mercy, no matter who they are!
不論是誰，我們都不留情
Whippersnapper!
自以為是的年輕人
I was so close.
我差點就到手了說
Why do I have such bad luck?
我為什麼運氣這麼背？
You only think about yourself and the immediate present.
你只想到自己，只顧當下
Someone so self-absorbed will never be blessed with good luck.
這麼自私的人 是絕對不會有好運降臨的
Shizuka!
閑！
Are you all right?
妳沒事吧？
Thank you!
謝謝你們
I'm really lucky…
你們全都來了
you all showed up!
我真的好幸運！
Wrong-minded people who get in my way should all become zombies!
那些礙事又錯誤的傢伙都該成為殭屍
I'm the one who is right!
我才是對的！
In my country,
在我的國家
it's normal to toss your cigarette butts on the ground as you walk.
走路抽菸或亂丟垃圾都是很正常的
Supermarket cashiers chew gum as they serve customers,
超市收銀員會嚼著口香糖服務客人
and vacuuming on Sunday, a day of rest, is rude because everyone wants to relax.
週日用吸塵器很無禮 因為大家都想休息
On your birthdays, you organize your own party and treat others to food.
生日時要自己規劃慶生會 請大家吃東西
I'm sure that this all sounds absurd to you.
這些事在妳聽來一定都很荒謬吧？
But that was normal life for me.
但是那種生活對我來說很正常
Are you trying to say I'm wrong too?
妳也想說我錯了嗎？
I don't give a damn about your culture!
我才不在乎妳的文化！
All wrong-minded people should just shut up and become zombies!
所有想法錯誤的人 都該閉上嘴趕快成為殭屍就對了
No way!
不會吧？
You took advantage of the zombies gathering here…
妳竟然利用聚集過來的殭屍…
to destroy the water wheel and cut the power?
毀掉水車，切斷電力？
That's just crazy.
太扯了
This is absolutely the wrong way of doing it.
這種做法絕對是錯誤的
There is no perfectly right way of doing things.
做事本來就沒有絕對正確的方法
There are all sorts of people and they make the world a colorful place.
正因存在各式各樣的人 世界才會如此繽紛
Perhaps instead of forcing what you thought was right on others,
也許強加自己覺得對的事 在別人身上時
you should have stopped and questioned whether you might have been wrong?
該被阻止 該停下來省視自己的是妳才對
This certainly is a problem.
這下麻煩了
I can't get down from here.
我下不去
Dad!
爸！
Don't open it!
別開門
Absolutely do not open it, Akira!
輝，絕對不能開門！
If you do, you'll be putting your mom and the others in danger!
你一開門 就會讓媽媽和其他人陷於危險
Dad.
爸
Just a few more.
再殺幾個就好
This is terrible.
太糟糕了
At a time like this?
竟然挑在這個時候？
Looks like my time has come at last.
看來我的日子終於到了
How pathetic.
真是可悲
Dad!
爸！
Higurashi?
日暮？
Why are you saving my dad?
你為什麼要救我爸？
So, I was thinking.
我在想
You're pretty tough, right?
你挺強悍的，對吧？
So, how can I make sure you become a zombie?
所以，我要怎麼樣 才能讓你變成殭屍呢？
That's when I got it.
這時我就想到
I found the perfect situation!
我找到完美的答案了！
Listen up.
聽好了
If you don't want me to kick your dad down, open that door and get zombified.
如果你不想要我把你爸踢下去 就打開門來變殭屍
You want to repay your parents, right?
你想回報父母，對吧？
Then show your dad just how good a son your are!
那就讓你老爸看看 你是多麼孝順的兒子啊！
What?
什麼？
Next Time: Hometown of the Dead III.
下一集：死者的家鄉-下